The Ole Bull Papers
Yale University Music Library
The Ole Bull Papers
1834-1906
Misc. Ms. 286
Yale University Music Library
1
(2 boxes)
Music and other materials by and about the Norwegian violinist and composer Ole Bull (1810-1880)
Bull, Ole, 1810-1880
Kohne, Ridley
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Ole Bull Papers were established in the Music Library of Yale University by Patricia Bull Smith Langdon, Olea Smith-Kaland, Stephen Bartlett Smith, and Shapleigh Smith in 1989.
Arrangement
In 4 series as follows: I. Music by Ole Bull. II. Music by others: manuscript copies. III. Music by others: printed works. IV. Miscellaneous items.
Scope and Contents
The Ole Bull Papers contain sketches, manuscript scores, or printed editions of 11 compositions by Bull. The Papers also hold music by other composers from Bull's personal library. Among the miscellaneous items are programs, printed works relating to Bull, and 13 manuscript receipts which document a series of concerts played by Bull in 1853 in Charleston, South Carolina.
Biographical / Historical
Ole Bull was born in Bergen, Norway on February 5, 1810. From an early age he showed a rare talent for the violin, and he made his solo debut in 1819. He took lessons from students of Viotti and Baillot, and also learned much from traditional Norwegian fiddlers, an influence that contributed to his unique style. Bull was interested in the design and construction of violins and bows, and by using a flatter bridge and a rounded bow, he was able to produce unusual polyphonic effects. He made many European concert tours, and he also spent a considerable amount of time in the United States, as a violinist, impresario, and promoter of an ill-fated Norwegian colony in Pennsylvania. Bull was known for his virtuosic and idiosyncratic performances, his personal charisma, and his Norwegian nationalism. (Norway was under Swedish control from 1814 to 1905.) Ole Bull died in Lysøen, Norway on August 17, 1880.
Music -- South Carolina -- Charleston -- 19th century; Violin and piano music -- Scores; Violin with orchestra -- Scores; Violinists -- Norway; Bull, Ole, 1810-1880
- Register (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Music by Ole Bull, Series I
  - [Adagio et rondo sur un thème de Paganini] Adagio et rondo pour le violon sur un thème de Paganini, 1 manuscript part (10 p.); 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General
    Holograph in ink.
    Solo violin part only.
  - [Adagio religioso, arr.] Adagio religioso, op. 1; nocturne, op. 2 pour violon avec orchestre ou piano / composé par Ole Bull. -- Leipzig: J. Schuberth, [1834], 1 score (7 p.) + 1 part (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Adagio religioso only.
    For violin and piano.
    Corrections in pencil.
    2 copies.
    Pl. no.: 630.631, 631a.
  - [Adagio religioso, arr.] Adagio religioso / Ole Bull. -- Leipzig: J. Schuberth, [1834], 1 score (7 p.) + 1 part (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    "Opus 1."
    Cover signed: "Olea Bull Voryhan."
    Pl. no.: 630.631., 631a.
  - [Adagio religioso, arr.] A mother's prayer = En moders bön; adagio religioso arranged for piano / by Ole Bull. -- New York: C.H. Ditson, [184-], 4 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Incomplete: Lacks p. 5-
    Pl. no.: 24410
  - [Carneval de Venide] Karneval / af Ole Bull., 1 manuscript score (2 p.) + 21 manuscript parts; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    For violin and string orchestra.:
    Parts for: vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc/db/pno/org.
    Corrections in ink and pencil.
  - [Concertos, violin, orchestra; no. 1, A major] Concert, a dur / af Ole Bull., 1 manuscript part; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Corrections pasted in.
    Part for: VlnII.
  - [Fantaisie et variations de bravoure sur un thème de Bellini] Fantaisie et variations de bravoure sur un thème de Bellini, 1 score (44 + 16 p.) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes reduction for piano.
    Bound with: Adagio religioso, op. 1.
    Pl. no.: 623., 631.
  - [Fantaisie et variations de bravoure sur un thème de Bellini, arr.] Fantaisie et variations de bravoure sur un thème de Bellini, 1 score (12 p.) + 1 part (11 p.); 37 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Arranged for violin and piano.
    Corrections
    Pl. no.: 622.623., a4604a
  - [Fantaisie et variations de bravoure sur un thème de Bellini, arr.] Fantasie and variationen über ein Thema von Bellini, op. 3 / Ole Bull. -- Leipzig: J. Schuberth, [1843], 1 score (19 p.) + 1 part (9 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Pl. no.: 622.623., 5922
  - [Fantaisie et variations de bravoure sur un thème de Bellini] Fantaisie et variations de bravoure sur un thème de Bellini pour violon avec orchestre ou piano, op. 3 / composées par Ole Bull. -- Hamburg :. Schuberth, [1843], 1 score (44 p.) + 27 parts; 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    For flI-II/obI-II/clI-II/bnI-II/hnI-II/tptI-II/tbnI-III/d/solo vln/vln I/vln II/vla/vc/db.
    Score includes reduction for piano.
    Performances and dates in pencil.
    Incomplete: Lacks cello part.
    Pl. no.: 623., 622.
  - [Fantaisie et variations de bravoure sur un thème de Bellini], 4 manuscript parts; 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Parts for: vlnI/vlnII/db.
    2 copies of db part.
    VlnI and VlnII dated, in ink: [Moscow, 31 March, in the year 1866]
    VlnI, in pencil: Gudbr. Böhn, C. Hansen, Christiana.
  - [Lilly Dale] Fantasia on Lilly Dale / composed by Ole Bull., 1 manuscript score (16 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Holograph, signed, in ink.
  - [Lilly Dale] Lilly Dale / Ole Bull., 1 manuscript score (11 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Corrections in pencil and ink.
  - [Nattergalen] Nattergalen, 1 manuscript score (14 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - [Pollacca guerriera] Pollacca guerriera, 3 manuscript parts; 30 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Corrections in pencil and pasted in.
    Incomplete: Lacks, all but vlnII/vlaI/db.
  - [Pollacca guerriera, arr.] Pollacca guerriera / van Ole Bull., 1 manuscript score; 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Corrections in pencil. _
  - [Recuerdos de Habana] Erindringer fra Havannah / Ole Bull., 17 manuscript parts; 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    For fl/ob/clI-II/bnI-II/hnI-II/tptI-II/tbn/tp/d/vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc and db.
    VlnI has title "Recuerdos de la Abana."
  - [Saetersbesog (Sketch)] Et Saeterbesog, 1 manuscript p. of music; 26 x 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Holograph in ink and pencil.
    Incomplete.
  - [Siciliano e tarantella] Siciliano e tarantella / comp. af Ole Bull., 1 manuscript score (68 p.); 34 cm. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    For violin and orchestra.
  - [Siciliano e tarantella] Siciliano, 1 manuscript part (6 p.); 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Solo violin part, with orchestral cues.
  - [Siciliano e tarantella, arr.] Siciliano e tarantelle / Ole Bull., 1 manuscript score (14 p.); 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Arranged for violin and organ.
  - [Siciliano e tarantella, arr. (Sketches)] Siciliano e tarantella, 25 manuscript p. of music; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Sketches, mainly towards an arrangement for violin and piano.
  - [Villspel i Lio] Vilspel i Lio / Ole Bull., 1 manuscript score (29 p.); 27 x 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Incomplete: Sections of score not filled in.
  - [Unidentified score], 1 manuscript score (20 p.); 27 x 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Incomplete: p. 14-33 only, many sections not filled in.
  - [Unidentified sketches], 25 manuscript p. of music; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Sketches, mainly towards solo violin parts and violin/piano works.
- Music by others: manuscript copies, Series II
  - Marche de S.A. la Khedive d'Egypte / par Iuppa Bey., Bey, Iuppa; 1 manuscript p. of music; 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    For piano.
    Copied in ink by Ole Bull (?)
    Dated: "Alexandria 1876 Fevrier."
  - [Didone: Nel duol che prova l'alma immorita, arr.] Nel duol the prova l'alma immorita; aria nell opera di Didone / composta da Vincenzo Ciampi., Ciampi, Vincenzo Legrenzio, 1719-1762; 1 manuscript score (2 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Incomplete: Lacks all after m. 43.
  - Bön / Fredrikke Egeberg., Egeberg, Fredrikke; 1 manuscript score (2 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    For voice and piano.
    Norwegian words.
    Signed at end: "B. Bjornson."
  - Andante, op. 86 / Mozart., Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791; 16 manuscript parts; various sizes. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    For vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc/db/obI-II/hnI-II.
    Various copyists' manuscripts in ink.
  - [Sonates avec les adagios brodés, no. 2] Sonate für violine mit unbeziffertem bass / von Pietro Nardini; nach der venezianischen ausgabe von 1760 für violine and pianoforte bearbeitet von Ferdinand David., Nardini, Pietro, 1722-1793; 1 manuscript score (8 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Signed at end: "Tho. a'Becket Sr., copyist."
- Music by others: printed works, Series III
  - [Ave Maria (Vocal version)] Ave Maria; mélodie religieuse / adaptée par Ch. Gounod. -- Mainz: B. Schott, [18--], Gounod, Charles, 1818-1893; 1 score (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    For voice and piano
    Latin, French, and German words.
    Pl. no.: 15886.
  - [Sonatas, violin, piano, no. 1, op. 8, F major] Sonate für pianoforte and violine, op. 8 / von Edvard Grieg. -- Leipzig: C.F. Peters, [18--], Grieg, Edvard, 1843-1907; 1 score (23 p.) + 1 part (8 p.); 31 cm. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Cover signed: "Ole Bull."
    Pl. no.: 4534
  - [Adagio et polonaise, violin, orchestra] Adagio et polonaise pour violon principal avec accompagnement d'orchestre / composés par Habeneck. -- Paris: Launer, [1986-], Habeneck, François Antoine, 1781-1849; 1 part (11 p.) (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Inscribed on cover: "To Mr. Ole Bull, in remembrance of many kindnesses. Charles N. Allen, Boston, Mass., Jany. 21/80."
    Pl. no.: 2909
  - Élégie pour violon avec piano / par Ridley Kohne. -- Budapest: Rozsavolgyi, [18--], Kohne, Ridley; 1 score (10 p.) + 1 part (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    On cover: Inscription from composer to Ole Bull.
    Pl. no.: 1924
  - [Fantaisies hongroises, C minor] Fantaisie hongroise pour violon avec piano / par Ridley Kohne. -- Leipzig: F. Kistner, [18--], Kohne, Ridley; 1 score (11 p.) + 1 part (4 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Pl. no.: 2285
  - [Fantaisies hongroises, D minor] Fantaisie hongroise sur un thème original pour le violon avec accompagnement de piano / par Ridley Kohne. -- Vienna: C.A. Spina, [18--], Kohne, Ridley; 1 score (19 p.) + 1 part (7 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Pl. no.: C.S.9583.
  - Mes adieux; rapsodies hongroises pour violon avec piano / par Ridley Kohne. -- Budapest: Rozsavolgyi, [18--], Kohne, Ridley; 1 score (7 p.) + 1 part (3 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Pl. no.: 1925
  - At twilight / by Isidora Martinez. -- Cincinnati: J. Church, c1906., Martinez, Isidora; 3 p. of music; 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    On cover: "To Mrs. Ole Bull, with compliments of Isidora Martinez."
    Pl. no.: 15297-2
  - [Concertos, violin, orchestra, K. 218, D major] Conzert (D dur) für die violine mit begleitung des orchesters / von W.A. Mozart. -- Offenbach: J. Andre, [18--], Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791; 1 part (19 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Pl. no.: 9404
  - [Concertos, violin, orchestra, K. 268, E major] Concerto, op. 76 / par W.A. Mozart. -- Mainz: B. Schott, [18--], Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791; 1 part (13 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Pl. no.: 17870.
  - [Concertos, violin, orchestra, K. 268, E major, arr.] Concerto pour le violon avec accompagnement d'orchestre ou de piano, op. 76 / composé par W.A. Mozart; arrangement de F.X. Gleichauf. -- Offenbach: J. Andre, [18--], Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791; 1 part (21 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Nouvelle édition.
    For piano with occasional violin cues.
    On cover: Inscription to Ole Bull from A. Feilitsen.
    Pl. no.: 1288.
  - [Quintets. Selections] Quintuors / de Mozart. -- Leipzig: C.F. Peeters, [18--], Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791; 5 parts (2 v.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Incomplete: Lacks all but vln II, v. 2.
    Contents: Quintetto I -- Quintetto II -- Quintetto III -- Quintetto IX -- Quintetto X (Horn in E) -- Quintetto X (Violoncello primo; in vece corno)
    Signed on cover: "Ole Bull."
    Pl. no.: 3651-3653, 3659a.b, 3696
  - [Quintets, clarinet, violins, viola, violoncello, K. 581, A major] Quintetto IX / W.A. Mozart. -- Leipzig: C.F. Peeters, [18--], Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791; 6 parts; 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    For cl/vlnI/vlnII/vla/vc, with optional parts for vlnI and vlaI to replace cl.
    Pl. no.: 3659a, 3659b.
  - [Quintets, clarinet, violins, viola, violoncello, K. 581, A major. Larghetto, arr.] Adagio aus Mozart's quintett, op. 108 / transcription von C. Schuberth. -- Leipzig: New York: J. Schuberth, [18--], Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791; 1 score (7 p.); 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    For violoncello-and piano.
    Pl. no.: 2018
  - [Sonatas, violin, piano] Sämmtliche duos für pianoforte and violine / W.A. Mozart. -- Braunschweig: H. Litolff, [18--], Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791; 1 score (2 v.); 32 cm. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Volume 1 only.
    On title page: Inscription from Ole Bull, dated 1869.
    Pl. no.: 2103-2120.
  - [S'kommt ein vogel geflogen, piano] S'kommt ein vogel geflogen; ein deutsches volkslied im style älterer und neuerer meister / von Siegfried Ochs. -- Heidelberg: E. Pfeiffer, [18--], Ochs, Siegfried, 1858-1929; 15 p. of music; 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Inscribed on cover.
    Pl. no.: E.P.1
  - [Sonatas, violin, continuo, B. g 5, G minor] Le trille du diable; sonate pour le violon / par Giuseppe Tartini; accompagnement de piano... par H. Leonard. -- Mainz: B. Schott, [18--], Tartini, Giuseppe, 1692-1770; 1 score (11 p.) + 1 part (5 p.); 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Pl. no.: S.F.1108
- Miscellaneous items, Series IV
  - 13 manuscript receipts relating to a series of concerts played by Ole Bull in Charleston, SC., Jan. 21-Feb. 4, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Scope and Contents
    1 Autograph letter signed (photocopy) from Ole Bull, in French.
    2 manuscript programs of Ole Bull's concerts. 1 in French. 1 in Russian.
    1 printed program of Ole Bull's last concert in Brooklyn, May 10, 1877.
  - Ole Bull's Gasger-Cellini violin, 30 p., ill.; 15 cm. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Ole-Bulls-Festen i "den norske forening" i København, 4 p., ill.; 27 x 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Ole Bull / Olav Lofthus, Lofthus, Olav; 1 leaf; 36 cm. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Printed poem.